Alexander Hollaender Papers 1955-1974 Mss.B.H717
American Philosophical Society
Alexander Hollaender Papers
1955-1974
Mss.B.H717
American Philosophical Society
4.0 Linear feet
Alexander Hollaender was a leading researcher on the genetic effects of radiation. Born in Samter, Germany, in 1898 and arriving in the United States in 1921, Hollaender was educated at the University of Wisconsin, receiving his AB, MA, and Ph.D. there. He served on the faculty at the University of Tennessee and the University of Tennessee-Oak Ridge Graduate School of Biomedical Sciences. He was director of the division of biology at the Atomic Energy Commission's Oak Ridge National laboratory from 1946 until 1966. The 4 linear feet of the Alexander Hollaender Papers contain incoming and outgoing correspondence and reports relating to the genetic effects of radiation, specifically atomic radiation. Also included are documents of the International Conference on the Peaceful Uses of Atomic Energy; the NAS Committee on the Biological Effects of Atomic Energy, Genetics Panel; the United Nations Scientific Committee on Atomic Radiation; and the World Health Organization all of which Hollaender was closely involved with.
Hollaender, Alexander, 1898-1986
Box 1-8
Physiology, Biochemistry, and Biophysics Note
Alexander Hollaender was educated at the University of Wisconsin, receiving his doctorate in physical chemistry in 1931. These were exciting times to be at Wisconsin, surrounded by scientists like Max Mason, Warren Weaver, John Warren Williams, and Theodor Svedberg, men who in the early 1930s would spearhead the merger of physics, chemistry, and biology under the aegis of the Rockefeller Foundation. Hollaender became an active participant in these intellectual and institutional endeavors. He remained associated with Wisconsin until 1937, working on problems of radiation genetics and chemical mutagenesis (he was one of the first researchers to point out the significance of nucleic acids in mutagenesis). He was also an adviser to the Rockefeller Foundation on the development of molecular biology, and was involved in administering Rockefeller Fellowships and projects of the National Research Council.
In 1937 Hollaender moved to the Washington Biophysics Institute of the National Institutes of Health as an associate biologist, and soon after was promoted as senior biophysicist, a position he held until 1950. By that time Hollaender had established himself as a world authority on radiation genetics. He served as director of the division of biology at the Atomic Energy Commission's Oak Ridge National Laboratory from 1946 to 1966, and as a senior research adviser from 1967 until his retirement in 1972. His personal papers have been deposited at the University of Tennessee.
The Hollaender Papers at the APS Library document his activities in postwar radiation genetics, a field addressing biological problems in relation to the newly unleashed powers of atomic energy. These communications, together with the files on radiation genetics, form an important source on the history of that field and its relations to social concerns, environmental issues, and cancer research.
Beadle, George Wells, 1903-1989 ( Includes correspondence regarding radiation genetics, National Academy of Sciences, and committee activities.) Correspondence (5 folders (30 items)) 1956-1959 English
Bronk, Detlev W. (Detlev Wulf), 1897-1975 Correspondence (9 items) 1955-1956 English
Campbell, Charles I. ( Includes correspondence regarding radiation genetics, National Academy of Sciences, and committee activities.) Correspondence (6 folders (38 items)) 1956-1957 English
Demerec, M. (Milislav), 1895-1966 Correspondence (2 items) 1957 English
Dobzhansky, Theodosius Grigorievich, 1900-1975 Correspondence (1 item) May 16, 1959 English
Emerson, Sterling Howard, 1900-1988 Correspondence (3 items) 1956 English
International Conference on Replication and Recombination of Genetic Material ( Concerns more current issues (1960s) in genetics and molecular biology.) Records (7 folders) 1965-1967 English
International Conference on the Peaceful Uses of Atomic Energy. 2nd, Geneva, 1958 ( Documents Hollaender's activities in postwar radiation genetics, a field addressing biological problems in relation to the newly unleashed powers of atomic energy. The Hollaender Papers also contain materials related to the 1st (1958) and 3rd (1964, Geneva) international conferences.) Records (41 folders) 1957-1958 English
Lederberg, Joshua Correspondence (1 item) March 10, 1958 English
Muller, H. J. (Hermann Joseph), 1890-1967 ( Includes correspondence regarding radiation genetics, National Academy of Sciences, and World Health Organization; folder entitled "Damage from Point Mutations in relation to Radiation Dose and Biological Conditions.") Correspondence (5 folders) 1956-1961 English
National Academy of Sciences. Committee on the Genetic Effects of Atomic Radiation ( Documents Hollaender's activities in postwar radiation genetics, a field addressing biological problems in relation to the newly unleashed powers of atomic energy.) Records (30 folders) 1955-1962 English
Neel, James V. (James Van Gundia), 1915-2000 Correspondence (10 items) 1956-1957 English
Perutz, Max F. Correspondence (2 items) 1963 English
Stern, Curt, 1902-1981 Correspondence (2 items) 1957 English
Sturtevant, Alfred Henry, 1891-1970 Correspondence (3 items) 1957 English
Symposium on Genetics in Medical Research ( Documents Hollaender's activities in postwar radiation genetics, a field addressing biological problems in relation to the newly unleashed powers of atomic energy.) Records (15 items) 1958 English
Weaver, Warren Correspondence (2 folders) 1955-1957 English
Workshop Conference on Space Radiation Biology ( Concerns more current issues (1960s) in genetics and molecular biology.) Records (6 items) 1964-1965 English
World Health Organization. Study Group on the Effect of Radiation on Human Genetics ( An active member of the World Health Organization (WHO), Hollaender headed a Study Group on the Effects of Radiation on Human Genetics, activities recorded in these folders.) Records (25 folders) 1955-1956 English
Genetics Note
This collection contains materials which relate to the history of genetics.
American Society of Human Genetics Records (8 folders) 1956-1963
Appleyard, Raymond K. Correspondence (25 items) 1956-1958
Beadle, George Wells Correspondence (30 items) 1956-1959
Campbell, Charles I. Correspondence (38 items) 1956-1957
Inter-American Symposium on the Peaceful Application of Nuclear Energy Records (10 folders) 1957
International Conference on Replication and Recombination of Genetic Material Records (7 folders) 1965-1967
International Conference on the Peaceful Uses of Atomic Energy. Second Conference Records (41 folders) 1957-1958
International Conference on the Peaceful Uses of Atomic Energy. Third Conference Records (2 folders) 1963
International Science Exhibition, Brussels Records (8 folders) 1957-1958
Kaplan, Martin M. Correspondence (18 folders) 1963-1965
Muller, Hermann Joseph Correspondence (6 folders) 1956-1961
National Academy of Sciences. Committee on the Genetic Effects of Atomic Radiation Records (30 folders) 1955-1962
National Research Council Correspondence (2 folders) 1966-1967
United Nations Scientific Committee on the Effects of Atomic Radiation Records (39 folders) 1956-1969
World Health Organization Records (5 folders) 1956-1965
World Health Organization. Proposal for Research Center Records (24 folders) 1963-1966
World Health Organization. Study Group on the Effect of Radiation on Human Genetics Records (18 folders) 1955-1956
Other Finding Aids note
The Hollaender Papers are also described in Bentley Glass' A Guide to the Genetics Collections of the APS.
Related Archival Materials note
The Archives of Radiation Biology at the University of Tennessee, Knoxville hold many of Hollaender's papers, records, and books on radiation biology. Additional papers of Hollaender can be found at the University of Texas, Galveston.
Additional Hollaender correspondence is located in the Demerec Papers (79 items).
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Acquired, 1974.
Scope and Contents note
The Alexander Hollaender Papers consist of 4 linear feet of correspondence to and from various geneticists as well as reports and correspondence of the assorted committees, conferences, and organizations in which Hollaender was involved. These papers only contain material from 1955 to 1974.
Included in the Hollaender papers are the records of the National Academy of Sciences committee on the Biological Effects of Atomic Energy. One of the goals of the committee was to outline the issues and problems concerning the scientific knowledge of the genetic effects of high-energy radiation and to suggest the path future research on the subject should take. The information contained in the Hollaender papers is primarily concerned with the criticism and revision of the various drafts of the committee reports, one published in 1956 and the other in 1960.
Hollaender was an active participant in the United Nations Scientific Committee on the Effects of Atomic Radiation. The information on this committee relates to a report prepared by the committee in 1958 and more specifically Hollaender's criticism of the report. Also found in the papers are records concerning published reports and publicly delivered papers of the Second International Conference on the Peaceful Uses of Atomic Energy.
Largely represented in the papers is Hollaender's activities in the World Health Organization. As a participant in this organization Hollaender was again concerned with the genetics effects of radiation, acting as chairman of a study group focused on the specific effects of radiation on humans. Records of a proposed World Health Research Center are also contained in the papers.
Biographical/Historical note
Geneticist Alexander Hollaender was born in Samter, Germany on 19 December 1898. He immigrated to the United States in 1921 around the age of 23 and became a naturalized citizen in 1927. He obtained his secondary education at the University of Wisconsin were he received his AB in 1929, his MA in 1930, and his Ph.D. in Physical Chemistry in 1931. While fulfilling his college requirements, Hollaender served as assistant instructor in physical chemistry. Hollaender continued his stay at the University of Wisconsin from 1931 until 1933 as instructor of Biology.
From early on in his career, Hollaender was interested in the problems of radiation biology and chemical mutagenesis. In 1934 he held the Rockefeller Foundation fellowship for the study of chemical radiation. Following that, he supervised a National Research Council project on radiation at Wisconsin from 1934 until 1937. Upon completion of the project, Hollaender moved to the Washington Biophysics Institute of the National Institute of Health as an associate biologist. After only a year he was promoted to senior biophysicist, a position he held until 1950. Concurrently, he served as director of the division of biology at the Atomic Energy Commission's Oak Ridge National laboratory from 1946 to 1966 where in 1967 he was promoted to senior research advisor, a position he held until 1972.
Hollaender continued to be involved in academics throughout his life. He served on the faculty of the University of Tennessee as a professor of radiation biology from 1957 and 1966. Subsequently he served as a professor of biomedical sciences at the University of Tennessee-Oak Ridge Graduate School of Biomedical Sciences from 1967 to 1972. During his lifetime Hollaender was a member and chairman of the National Academy of Sciences-National Research Council committee on photobiology, a member and chairman of the subcommittee on radiobiology for the National Research Council, and served as a civilian advisor to many governmental agencies. He was president of the Radiation Research Society in 1954-1955, and of the International Association for Radiation Research from 1962 until 1966. He died in Washington, D.C. on 6 December 1986.
Beadle, George Wells, 1903-1989; Bronk, Detlev W., (Detlev Wulf), 1897-1975; Campbell, Charles I.; Crow, James Franklin, 1916-; Demerec, M., (Milislav), 1895-1966; Dobzhansky, Theodosius Grigorievich, 1900-1975; Emerson, Sterling; Glass, Bentley, 1906-2005; International Conference on the Peaceful Uses of Atomic Energy; Kaplan, Martin M.; Muller, H. J., (Hermann Joseph), 1890-1967; National Academy of Sciences. (U.S.); Neel, James V., (James Van Gundia), 1915-2000; Oak Ridge National Laboratory.; Perutz, Max F., 1914-2002; Plough, Harold Henry, 1892-; Stern, Curt, 1902-1981; Sturtevant, A. H. (Alfred Henry), 1891-; United Nations. Scientific Committee on the Effects of Atomic Radiatio.; Weaver, Warren, 1894-1978; World Health Organization.; Genetics; Nuclear energy; Radiation--Physiological effect
- Alexander Hollaender Papers, 1955-1974; 4 lin. feet
  - Abbatt, John D., 1957; 2 items (Box 1)
  - Alexander, Peter, 1957-1958; 13 items (Box 1)
  - Annual Report, 1962; 1 item; American Genetics Association (Box 1)
  - American Philosophical Society, 1974 January 18; 1 item (Box 1)
  - American Society of Human Genetics, 1956-1963; 8 folders (Box 1)
    American Society of Human Genetics; Committee activities; International Congress of Human Genetics; Scientific organizations, meetings, programs
    - Folder 1, 1956; 5 items (Box 1)
    - Folder 2, 1957 April; 9 items (Box 1)
    - Folder 3, 1957 July; 3 items (Box 1)
    - Folder 4, 1958; 2 items (Box 1)
    - Folder 5, 1959; 3 items (Box 1)
    - Folder 6, 1960-1961; 9 items (Box 1)
    - Folder 7, 1962; 6 items (Box 1)
    - Folder 8, 1963; 4 items (Box 1)
  - Anderson, Donald R., 1965 April 26; 1 item (Box 1)
  - Appleyard, Raymond K., 1956-1958; 3 folders (25 items) (Box 1)
    Committee activities; Radiation genetics; United Nations Scientific Committee on the Effects of Atomic Radiation
    - Folder 1, 1956; 8 items (Box 1)
    - Folder 2, 1957; 10 items (Box 1)
    - Folder 3, 1958; 7 items (Box 1)
  - Bacq, Z. M., 1958-1963; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Folder 1, 1958, 1963; 6 items (Box 1)
    - Folder 2, 1963; 6 items (Box 1)
  - Basile, Renato, 1973 September 27; 1 item (Box 1)
  - Beadle, George W., 1956-1959; 5 folders (30 items) (Box 1)
    Committee activities; National Academy of Sciences -- Committee on the Biological Effects of Atomic Radiation - Genetics Panel; Radiation genetics
    - Folder 1, 1956; 10 items (Box 1)
    - Folder 2, 1957; 6 items (Box 1)
    - Folder 3, 1958; 9 items (Box 1)
    - Folder 4, 1958; 3 items (Box 1)
    - Folder 5, 1959; 2 items (Box 1)
  - Brodie, Bernard B., 1964; 3 items (Box 1)
  - Bronk, Detlev W., 1955-1956; 9 items (Box 1)
  - Brown, Spencer W., 1973-1974; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Folder 1, 1973-1974; 1 items (Box 1)
    - Folder 2, 1974; 7 items (Box 1)
  - Brucer, Marshall, 1958 August 1; 1 item (Box 1)
  - Btesh, S, 1965; 3 items (Box 1)
  - Calvin, Melvin, 1957; 3 items (Box 1)
  - Campbell, Charles I., 1956-1957; 6 folders (38 items) (Box 1)
    - Folder 1, 1956; 11 items (Box 1)
    - Folder 2, 1956; 13 items (Box 1)
    - Folder 3, 1957; 4 items (Box 1)
    - Folder 4, 1957; 6 items (Box 1)
    - Folder 5, 1957; 2 items (Box 1)
    - Folder 6, 1957; 2 items (Box 1)
  - Casartelli, Cacilda, 1973 September 21; 1 item (Box 1)
  - Caspersson, Torbjoern, 1956 September 5; 1 item (Box 1)
  - Charpie, Robert A., 1957 September 18; 1 item (Box 1)
  - Chase, Herman B., 1965 April 20; 1 item (Box 1)
  - Christensen, B. Chr., 1955-1958; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Folder 1, 1955-1956; 8 items (Box 1)
    - Folder 2, 1957-1958; 2 items (Box 1)
  - The Atomic Age and Its Risks, 1957 October 7; 1 item; Christensen, B. Chr. (Box 1)
  - Chu, Ernest H. Y., 1973; 2 items (Box 1)
  - Congdon, Charles C., 1958; 2 items (Box 1)
  - Cottier, H., 1965; 2 items (Box 1)
  - Crow, James F., 1960-1961; 4 items (Box 1)
  - Demerec, Milislav, 1957; 2 items (Box 1)
  - Dobson, R. Lowry, 1959; 2 items (Box 1)
  - Dobzhansky, Theodosius, 1959 May 16; 1 item (Box 1)
  - Dorolle, P., 1958; 2 items (Box 1)
  - Dunham, Charles L., 1956-1957; 4 items (Box 1)
  - Endicott, Kenneth, 1964 June 9; 1 item (Box 1)
  - Emerson, Sterling, 1956; 3 items (Box 1)
  - Errera, Maurice, 1957; 2 items (Box 1)
  - Failla, G, 1958; 3 items (Box 1)
  - Federation of American Scientists, 1956; 2 items (Box 1)
  - Gardner, Edward R., 1960; 5 items (Box 1)
  - Genetics Society of America, 1956; 2 items (Box 1)
  - Glass, Bentley, 1956; 2 items (Box 1)
  - Gopal-Ayengar, A. R., 1956; 3 items (Box 1)
  - Report of Trip to Who, Geneva, Switzerland, 1963, March 4-7; 2 items; Hollaender, Alexander, 1898-1986 (Box 1)
  - Inter-American Symposium on the Peaceful Application of Nuclear Energy, 1957; 10 folders (Box 2)
    Conferences and symposia; Political issues -- Atomic energy; Radiation genetics
    - Folder 1, 1957 May 13-17; 1 item (Box 2)
    - Folder 2, 1957; 1 item (Box 2)
    - Folder 3, 1957; 1 item (Box 2)
    - Folder 4, 1957; 6 items (Box 2)
    - Folder 5, 1957; 4 items (Box 2)
    - Folder 6, 1957; 8 items (Box 2)
    - Folder 7, 1957; 12 items (Box 2)
    - Folder 8, 1957; 5 items (Box 2)
    - Folder 9, 1957; 6 items (Box 2)
    - Folder 10, 1957; 2 items (Box 2)
  - International Cell Research Organization, 1966; 1 item (Box 2)
  - International Conference on Replication and Recombination of Genetic Material, 1967, 1965-1967; 7 folders (Box 2)
    Conferences and symposia; Genetics
    - Folder 1, 1965; 5 items (Box 2)
    - Folder 2, 1965; 9 items (Box 2)
    - Folder 3, 1966; 12 items (Box 2)
    - Folder 4, 1966; 9 items (Box 2)
    - Folder 5, 1966; 6 items (Box 2)
    - Folder 6, 1966-1967; 9 items (Box 2)
    - Folder 7, 1967; 11 items (Box 2)
  - International Conference on the Peaceful Uses of Atomic Energy (2nd: 1958: Geneva, Switzerland), 1957-1958; 22 folders (Box 2)
    - Folder 1, 1958; 4 items (Box 2)
    - Folder 2, 1958; 1 item (Box 2)
    - Folder 3, 1958; 1 item (Box 2)
    - Folder 4, 1958; 1 item (Box 2)
    - Folder 5, 1958; 6 items (Box 2)
    - Folder 6, 1958; 6 items (Box 2)
    - Folder 7, 1958; 2 items (Box 2)
    - Folder 8, 1958 October 20; 1 item (Box 2)
    - Folder 9, 1958 October 20; 1 item (Box 2)
    - Folder 10, 1958; 3 items (Box 2)
    - Folder 11, 1958; 6 items (Box 2)
    - Folder 12, 1957; 7 items (Box 2)
    - Folder 13, 1957-1958; 10 items (Box 2)
    - Folder 14, 1957-1958; 11 items (Box 2)
    - Folder 15, 1958; 9 items (Box 3)
    - Folder 16, 1958; 13 items (Box 3)
    - Folder 17, 1958; 19 items (Box 3)
    - Folder 18, 1958; 16 items (Box 3)
    - Folder 19, 1958; 4 items (Box 3)
    - Folder 20, 1958; 6 items (Box 3)
    - Folder 21, 1958; 11 items (Box 3)
    - Folder 22, 1958; 3 items (Box 3)
  - International Conference on the Peaceful Uses of Atomic Energy (2nd: 1958: Geneva, Switzerland). Papers, 6 folders (Box 3)
    - Folder 1, 1958; 2 items (Box 3)
    - Folder 2, 1958; 1 item (Box 3)
    - Folder 3, 1958; 1 item (Box 3)
    - Folder 4, 1958; 1 item (Box 3)
    - Folder 5, 1958; 2 items (Box 3)
    - Folder 6, 1958; 2 items (Box 3)
  - International Conference on the Peaceful Uses of Atomic Energy (2nd: 1958: Geneva, Switzerland). Papers (Abstracts), 9 folders (Box 3)
    - Folder 1, 1958; 10 items (Box 3)
    - Folder 2, 1958; 2 items (Box 3)
    - Folder 3, 1958; 2 items (Box 3)
    - Folder 4, 1958; 3 items (Box 3)
    - Folder 5, 1958; 1 item (Box 3)
    - Folder 6, 1958; 1 item (Box 3)
    - Folder 7, 1958; 2 items (Box 3)
    - Folder 8, 1958; 3 items (Box 3)
    - Folder 9, 1958; 4 items (Box 3)
  - International Conference on the Peaceful Uses of Atomic Energy (2nd: 1958: Geneva, Switzerland). Reports, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Folder 1, 1958; 11 items (Box 3)
    - Folder 2, 1958; 5 items (Box 3)
    - Folder 3, 1958; 3 items (Box 3)
    - Folder 4, 1958; 2 items (Box 3)
  - International Conference on the Peaceful Uses of Atomic Energy (3rd: 1964: Geneva, Switzerland), 1963; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Folder 1, 1963; 10 items (Box 3)
    - Folder 2, 1963; 2 items (Box 3)
  - International Congress of Human Genetics (1st: 1956: Copenhagen), 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Folder 1, 1956; 5 items (Box 4)
    - Folder 2, 1956; 1 item (Box 4)
  - Opening Remarks, 1958 August 11; 1 item; International Congress of Radiation Research (1st: 1958) (Box 4)
  - International Commission on Radiological Protection, 1956; 2 items (Box 4)
  - International Genetics Symposia (1956: Tokyo and Kyoto, Japan), 1955-1956; 7 items (Box 4)
  - International Science Exhibition, Brussels, 1958, 1957-1958; 8 folders (Box 4)
    Conferences and symposia; Scientific organizations, meetings, programs
    - Folder 1, 1958; 1 item (Box 4)
    - Folder 2, 1957; 3 items (Box 4)
    - Folder 3, 1957; 9 items (Box 4)
    - Folder 4, 1957; 4 items (Box 4)
    - Folder 5, 1957; 6 items (Box 4)
    - Folder 6, 1957; 7 items (Box 4)
    - Folder 7, 1957; 5 items (Box 4)
    - Folder 8, 1958; 4 items (Box 4)
  - Joint Institute for Nuclear Research, 1958; 1 item (Box 4)
  - The Effect of Radiation on Humans, n.d.; 1 item; Jones, Hardin B. (Box 4)
  - Kaplan, Martin M., 1963-1965; 18 folders (Box 4)
    Oak Ridge National Laboratory; World Health Organization, United Nations
    - Folder 1, 1963 March; 4 items (Box 4)
    - Folder 2, 1963 March; 6 items (Box 4)
    - Folder 3, 1963 April-May; 11 items (Box 4)
    - Folder 4, 1963 June-July; 6 items (Box 4)
    - Folder 5, 1963 July-August; 13 items (Box 4)
    - Folder 6, 1963 August-October; 10 items (Box 4)
    - Folder 7, 1963 October-November; 10 items (Box 4)
    - Folder 8, 1963 December-1964 January; 7 items (Box 4)
    - Folder 9, 1964 January-March; 14 items (Box 4)
    - Folder 10, 1964 March-May; 8 items (Box 4)
    - Folder 11, 1964 August; 6 items (Box 4)
    - Folder 12, 1964 September; 3 items (Box 4)
    - Folder 13, 1964 September; 9 items (Box 4)
    - Folder 14, 1964 October; 10 items (Box 4)
    - Folder 15, 1965 January-February; 11 items (Box 4)
    - Folder 16, 1965-1966; 10 items (Box 4)
    - Folder 17, 1965 July; 4 items (Box 4)
    - Folder 18, n.d.; 13 items (Box 4)
  - Kemp, Tage, 1955-1956; 12 items (Box 4)
  - Kimball, R. F., n.d.; 2 items (Box 4)
  - Kiorpes, Anthony L., 1970 March 19; 1 item (Box 4)
  - Komai, Taku, 1956; 2 items (Box 4)
  - Kondratuk, Mrs. H. Z., 1965 April 20; 1 item (Box 4)
  - Lederberg, Joshua, 1958 March 10; 1 item (Box 4)
  - Lefevre, George, jr., 1973-1974; 4 items (Box 4)
  - Letter - Unknown Identity, n.d.; 1 item (Box 4)
  - Lotz, William E., 1965; 2 items (Box 4)
  - Livingston, Robert B., 1963; 5 items (Box 4)
  - Luska, Bertha, 1957; 10 items (Box 4)
  - MaClean's, 1956; 2 items (Box 4)
  - Malley, Margaret M., 1969; 2 items (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1964; 1 item (Box 4)
  - Muller, H. J. (Hermann Joseph), 1956-1961; 5 folders (Box 4)
    Committee activities; National Academy of Sciences -- Committee on the Biological Effects of Atomic Radiation - Genetics Panel; Radiation genetics; World Health Organization, United Nations
    - Folder 1, 1956; 6 items (Box 4)
    - Folder 2, 1956; 13 items (Box 4)
    - Folder 3, 1957; 6 items (Box 4)
    - Folder 4, 1959-1961; 4 items (Box 4)
    - Damage from Point Mutations in relation to Radiation Dose and Biological Conditions, 1 item (Box 4)
  - The Frequency of Spontaneous Mutations at Individual Loci in Drosophila, 2 items; Muller, H. J.; Valencia, J.I.; Valencia, R.M. (Box 4)
  - Are X-rays Dangerous to You?, 1957; 1 item; Murray, Dwight H. (Box 4)
  - Nakao, Y, 1956; 2 items (Box 5)
  - National Academy of Engineering., 1970; 2 items (Box 5)
  - National Academy of Sciences. Committee on the Genetic Effects of Atomic Radiation, 1955-1962; 30 folders (Box 5)
    - Folder 1, 1955; 13 items (Box 5)
    - Folder 2, 1955-1956; 3 items (Box 5)
    - Folder 3, 1956; 3 items (Box 5)